Guide to the José Carrillo de Albornoz (Duke of Montemar) papers, circa 1710-1746 RL.11664
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
José Carrillo de Albornoz (Duke of Montemar) papers
circa 1710-1746
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Carrillo de Albornoz, José, duque de Montemar
RL.11664
10 Linear Feet 25 volumes; mostly disbound. Original bindings retained.
Collection contains 26 volumes, 23 of them being papers, and printed pieces. The papers document domestic and foreign policy during the reign of Philip V. A small sampling of topics include the armed strength of European powers, the Catalan campaigns of 1710-1720, Montemar's time as Minister of War, conscription, Catalonia, the War of Jenkins' Ear, hostilities in America, the Corps of Carabineers, artillery and weaponry, Spanish finances, the War of Polish Succession, proposed system of free hospitals, army uniforms, and Montemar's time as Inspector-General of Cavalry. Items include official reports to and from Montemar, a 35-page poem on the Battle of Brihuega 1710, Montemar's letterbook, governors' orders, and letterbook of the Conde de Montemar.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The collection was passed by descent to the 16th Conde de Altamira. The papers were sold by Altamira in about 1865 and were bought from a French bookseller by Sir Thomas Phillipps in 1870. They were sold as part of a larger lot of Montemar's papers at Sotheby's on June 26th 1973. Duke purchased the collection in 1981 from Quevedo Rare Books and Manuscript of London. Most of the items still retain their Phillipps catalog numbers.
Historical Note
José Carrillo de Albornoz y Montiel (1671-1747) was a Spanish nobleman and military leader. He was the 1st Duke of Montemar, Viceroy of Sicily (1734-1737), and Minister of War for Spain (1737-1741).
Collection Overview
Collection contains 26 volumes, 23 of them being papers, and printed pieces. The papers document domestic and foreign policy during the reign of Philip V. A small sampling of topics include the armed strength of European powers, the Catalan campaigns of 1710-1720, Montemar's time as Minister of War, conscription, Catalonia, the War of Jenkins' Ear, hostilities in America, the Corps of Carabineers, artillery and weaponry, Spanish finances, the War of Polish Succession, proposed system of free hospitals, army uniforms, and Montemar's time as Inspector-General of Cavalry. Items include official reports to and from Montemar, a 35-page poem on the Battle of Brihuega 1710, Montemar's letterbook, governors' orders, and a letterbook of the Conde de Montemar.
Polish Succession, War of, 1733-1738; Anglo-Spanish War, 1718-1720; Anglo-Spanish War, 1739-1748; Sicily (Italy) -- History -- 18th century; Spain -- History -- 18th century; Spain -- History -- Philip V, 1700-1746; Letterbooks; Orders (military records); Carrillo de Albornoz, José, duque de Montemar.
- Information folder (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Contains background information on the collection, dealer descriptions, and extensive notes taken during initial processing. There are handwritten, item-level descriptions for many of the manuscripts in the collection.
- Catalonia, 1712-1714; 97 items Folio, contemporary vellum. (Box 2, Volume 1)
  Letterbook of the Conde de Montemar for the years 1712-14, written while Governor of Saragossa and containing copies of 97 letters to the Marques de Bedmar (Minister of War), Marques de Grimaldi, Princesse des Ursins, the King, the Marques de Castelar, the Prince of T'serclaes de Tilly and others. They include 31 letters to the Duke of Berwick and others written during the Siege of Barcelona 1713-14 and various plans for advances on the Aragon front (made irrelevant by the Spanish defeat at Almenara).
- Suzesos militares, 1710-1716; 13 items 12 manuscripts and 1 printed pamphlet (Box 3, Volume 2)
  Includes a 35-page poem on the Battle of Brihuega 1710, 'Diario de la carnpana del ano de 40', account by Baltasar de Guevara of the activities of five galleys off Corfu, reports on the fortification of Porto Longone on Elba (of which Montemar was appointed Governor in 1715), etc.
- Papeles tocantes a estado y guerra y Pragmaticas, 1702-1728; 47 items
  Materials concern the Catalan campaigns of 1710-20, the diplomatic campaigns of Ripperda etc. Includes a long report by Montemar himself on the state of Catalonia, a memorial by Gabriel de Roxas y Loyola denying the King's obligation to compensate those whose houses were demolished for the construction of the citadel of Barcelona (Montjuich), a report by the Marques de Castelar on the state of Catalan fortresses, a detailed project for Reviving Catalan trade and navigation, etc.
  - Papeles tocantes a estado y guerra y Pragmaticas (parts 1-3), 1702-1728; File; 15 items (Box 4, Volume 3)
  - Papeles tocantes a estado y guerra y Pragmaticas (parts 4-10), 1702-1728; 32 items (Box 5, Volume 3)
- Catalonia: Instruccion para el Servicio Uniforme, que se ha de hazer en todas las plazas del Principado de Cataluña, 1719 January 1; 340 pages Folio, contemporary vellum with flap-and-loop catch (Box 6, Volume 4)
  Detailed orders, in 26 chapters and 630 paragraphs, for the governors and garrisons of the fortresses of Catalonia. The second half of the heading on f1, including the words printed above in square brackets, and all the writing on the last two pages have been inked over, but the orders appear to have been issued by the Marquis of Ciudad Rodrigo from Barcelona on 1 January 1719.
- Papeles politicos y militares, 1721-1726; 48 items 48 manuscripts (Box 7, Volume 5)
  Materials largely relate to Catalonia. Includes a long 'Instrucción para el Govierno político de Catthalunia' by the Marques de Castelrodrigo (1721); account by Montemar himself of ceremonies observed by him on various occasions in Barcelona (82 pp); 'Instrucciones para el mando general militar de el exercito y Principado de Cattaluna', 1721, 2 copies; a memorial on the increase of robbery and crime in general (1724); correspondence with the Marques de Risbourg and the Marques de Castelrodrigo on the wartime organization of Catalonia, with reports on the production of bread, distribution of meat, etc.
- Letterbook of outgoing correspondence of Montemar, 1722 June 13-1724 February 5; 252 items 223 copies of letters, 13 duplicate copies, and 16 returns or reports Folio, contemporary vellum with flap (Box 8, Volume 6)
  Montemar's letter-book for the period 13 June 1722 to 5 February 1724, written while commanding officer in Catalonia, mostly to the Minister of War, the Marques de Castelar; containing 223 copies of letters, plus 13 duplicate copies, and including 16 returns or reports, on guns and swords held by cavalry regiments, on the Barcelona sabre factories, etc. A scrap of material, a sample of the lining of the uniform of the Seville Regiment is attached to p. 228. With an index.
- Tocante a Cavalleria, 1724-1745; 4 Volumes
  Four volumes containing about 235 mss., mainly dating from Montemar's period of office as Inspector-General of Cavalry. This large and interesting collection of papers includes correspondence with the Marques de la Ensenada, Sebastian de la Quadra and other ministers, together with letters to and from the Inspectors of Cavalry who worked under Montemar, on every subject to do with the cavalry; a long report by Montemar to Castelar on breeding horses for the cavalry; estimates supplies for troops passing through France, confidential reports on officers, dragoon regiments, the progress of the Italian War, etc.
  - Tocante a Cavalleria, no.1, 1736-1745; 53 items 53 manuscripts (Box 9, Volume 7)
  - Tocante a Cavalleria, no.2, 1724-1745; 43 items 43 manuscripts (Box 10, Volume 8)
  - Tocante a Cavalleria, no.3, 1741-1745 (Box 11, Volume 9)
  - Tocante a Cavalleria, no.4, 1737-1741; 32 items 32 manuscripts (Box 12, Volume 10)
- Papeles tocantes a los caravineros, 1730; 72 items (Box 13, Volume 11)
  72 letters and papers on the Corps of Carabineers, of which Montemar was appointed Inspector in 1730, including letters by Jose Patino and the Marques de Castelar and a long and interesting petition to Philip V by Montemar, recounting his service career.
- Encomiendas y pensiones sobre obispados, 1733-1738; 51 items (Box 14, Volume 12)
  Describes the plan to put the burden of paying pensions to those wounded in the War of Polish Succession on bishoprics.
- Varios Proyectos, 1736; 27 items (Box 15, Volume 13)
  Includes 'Proyecto para la Guerra de Portugal,' copies of a letter from the Marques de San Gil to Horace Walpole in Hanover about hostilities in America, and Walpole's reply (1736), paper about events in Buenos Aires following the arrival of Brigadier Salzedo and his attempt to organize the frontiers of Sacramento Colony (1736), together with other reports on foreign policy and trade; a project for a state lottery with 3 printed slips of lottery winners in Rome, Naples and Milan; various projects for an Italian war, by Moistemas' and others.
- Sobre la Artilleria y Saludos y Viveres Armamentos Municion..., 1736-1739; 2 Volumes
  Two volumes, about 75 pieces on artillery and weaponry, including a pen and wash drawing of a salvage ship [removed to oversize folder] and another of a musket, reports on the cannon-foundry at Seville, on the supply of gun-metal, on the state of the Madrid arsenal, on arms shipped from Leghorn to Barcelona in 1736, projects for a multi-barreled rifle and for flares, a long memorandum on the organization of the artillery, an account of the proofing and marking of firearms, and other similar pieces, including 10 privately printed petitions, mainly sent to Montemar as Minister of War.
  - Sobre la Artilleria y Saludos, 1736-1739; 57 items (Box 16, Volume 14)
  - Viveres, Armamentos, Municion..., 1736; 35 items 27 manuscript reports and 8 printed items (Box 17, Volume 15)
- Sobre hospitales, camas y utensilios de toda España, 1737; 62 items 55 manuscripts and 7 printed pieces (Box 18, Volume 16)
  Concerning Montemar's attempt to set up a system of free hospitals in every Spanish province for sick or wounded soldiers (1737).
- Sobre Tropas de las Potencias de la Europa, 1736-1737; 45 items 44 manuscripts and 1 printed booklet (Box 19, Volume 17)
  Reports on the armed strength of various European powers: Portugal, France, the Empire, Holland, Hesse-Cassel, Prussia, Russia and the Ottoman Empire, among others.
- Sobre Ynglaterra, 1739-1740; 40 items 38 manuscripts and 2 printed pieces (Box 20, Volume 18)
  Montemar's papers dealing with the War of Jenkins' Ear, 1739-40, showing the difficulties Spain had in making war on a maritime power. They include four memorials, by a parish priest of Cuenca, a certain Maxim de Bouchet, a captain of cavalry and an anonymous memorialist, making suggestions for the prosecution of the war, either by a landing in Scotland or by striking at England's trade (a long minute, presumably by Montemar, recommends forming a joint stock company in Seville to operate the Asiento in place of England). One proposal is to muster an army of Irish Catholic emigres, to be recruited by missionaries in Ireland. Letters include letters of Conde de Itre, Corunna, 6 January 1740, describing the shortage of wheat and the need to disperse the troops concentrated there for a landing in the United Kingdom; Joseph Francisco de Alos, 16 pp 4to, on the application of the royal decree forbidding trade with England; a copy of a letter from Montemar to Villarias about the British squadron cruising off Cape St Vincent; and copies of two reports on British abuses of their right under the Treaty of Utrecht to send one trading ship a year to the Spanish American colonies, 1722. There are intelligence reports of British naval and military strength, of the strength of a British squadron calling at Lisbon and the stores supplied to it, of British men-o-war with their captains' names, and two, from French sources, of men-o-war in commission and of British political parties.
- Sobre vecindarios y quintas, 1712-1741; 20 items 15 manuscripts and 5 printed pieces (Box 21, Volume 19)
  Papers on population returns, conscription, forced levies, etc.
- Ynstruir al Ministerio de la Guerra, 1737-1741; 84 items 82 manuscripts and 2 printed pieces
  Three volumes dating from Montemar's time as Minister of War relate to duties of the secretariat, memorials on finance, reports on individual officers, on troop strengths, etc.
  - Ynstruir al Ministerio de la Guerra, no.2, 1737-1741 (Box 22, Volume 20)
  - Ynstruir al Ministerio de la Guerra, no.3, 1737-1741 (Box 23, Volume 21)
  - Ynstruir al Ministerio de la Guerra, no.4, 1737-1741 (Box 24, Volume 22)
- Sobre asientos de bestuarios, 1737-1746; 56 items 55 manuscripts and 1 printed item (Box 25, Volume 23)
  A volume entirely devoted to army uniforms and contracts for their supply.
- Comisarious ordenadores y de geurra y su reforma, 1738-1739; 13 items (Box 26, Volume 24)
  Ten official reports to and from Montemar on the officers of the commissariat.
- Papeles de consecuencia, 1709-1743; 10 items 9 manuscripts and one printed item
  - Papeles de consecuencia, no. 1, 1709-1743 (Box 27, Volume 25)
  - Papeles de consecuencia, no. 2, 1737-1743 (Box 27, Volume 26)
- Pen and wash drawing of a salvage ship, circa 1736 (Oversize-folder 1)